Finding aid to the Harriet Bliss Ford papers CA.MS.00361
Smith College Archives
Harriet Bliss Ford papers
1877-1964
Smith College Archives
Ford, Harriet (Bliss), 1876-1964
CA.MS.00361
1.667 linear feet (5 containers)
Member of the Class of 1899 and Resident Trustee from 1931 to 1964. Collection contains correspondence, reports, clippings, publications, and photos.
Biographical / Historical
Harriet Chalmers Bliss Ford was born in 1876 in New York City. She attended the Mary A. Burnham School and graduated with Smith College's Class of 1899. She married George Burdett Ford, an architect and city planner, in 1912. From the time of her graduation until her marriage, Ford worked as an editor for Century Magazine. Participating as a member of the National Board of the YWCA beginning in 1924, Ford served as the organization's third vice-president, and volunteered for the New York Smith College Club and the University Club. During WWI, Ford worked in close contact with the Paris headquarters of the American Red Cross for two years and acted as chairman of the Paris committee of the Smith College Relief Unit in France. Ford served as the first chairman of the Alumnae Fund Committee of Smith College from 1927-1929, and as the director of the Alumnae Association from 1925-1928. In addition to her work with the Alumnae Association, Ford was also on the Board of Trustees from 1928-1936, and was a resident trustee from 1931 until the end of her life. Ford was also active in the National Committee on the Cause and Cure of War, and was named the organization's administrative chairman in 1937. Living in New York City for several years, Ford eventually returned to Northampton in 1941 and joined the committee to study and make recommendations for a charter for Northampton and the city's Tercentary. During World War II, she served as chief of the Office of Price Administration for Northampton and the surrounding area. Ford died on February 20, 1964 at the age of 87 in Northampton, Massachusetts after a long illness.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, reports, clippings, publications, notes, and photos. Included in the collection are numerous photograph albums, detailing the life of Harriet Bliss Ford, as well as her own poetry. There is also numerous material relating to the various organizations and committees she was a part of, as well as documents relating to her position as Resident Trustee at the college. There is also material relating to her husband, George Burdett Ford, including his book Out of the Ruins.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into five series:
SERIES I. GENERAL
SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
SERIES III. SPEECHES
SERIES IV: TOURS
SERIES V: PUBLICATIONS
Conditions Governing Access
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Harriet Bliss Ford papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Related Material
Additional papers of Harriet Bliss Ford are located in the Sophia Smith Collection.
- SERIES I. GENERAL
  - General, 1899-1935; undated (Box 271, Folder 1)
  - Biographical record, 1935-1964 (Box 271, Folder 2)
  - Capen House song and Saturday courses, 1935 (Box 271, Folder 3)
  - Century of Progress Exposition (Smith booth materials), 1933-1934 (Box 271, Folder 4)
  - European recovery plan (Marshall Plan): correspondence, articles, pamphlets, 1948 (Box 271, Folder 5)
  - Fight for Freedom organization materials: correspondence, mailings, propaganda, 1941-1942 (Box 271, Folder 6)
  - Five and seven college articles and correspondence, 1932-1933; undated (Box 271, Folder 7)
  - Ford, George Burdett: obituaries, articles, letters of condolence, Out of the Ruins, 1919-1941 (Box 271, Folder 8)
  - French relief/Smith College Relief Unit, 1945-1946 (Box 271, Folder 9)
  - League of Women Voters: notes and bulletin, 1952; undated (Box 271, Folder 10)
  - Mss - Pearman, Mabel Capelle (1899), undated (Box 271, Folder 11)
  - Mss - Summering on Taylor Court, undated (Box 271, Folder 12)
  - Neilson, William Allan - chair of research, 1935 (Box 271, Folder 13)
  - Neilson, William Allan - death/Alumnae Association, 1946 (Box 271, Folder 14)
  - Neilson, William Allan - dinners, 1929 (Box 271, Folder 15)
  - Neilson, William Allan - dinners, 1937 (Box 271, Folder 16)
  - Neilson, William Allan - portraits, 1929 (Box 271, Folder 17)
  - Neilson, William Allan - scholarships, 1932-1933 (Box 271, Folder 18)
  - Neilson, William Allan - speech, 1937 (Box 271, Folder 19)
  - Photographs - index, undated (Box 271, Folder 20)
  - Photographs, 1877-1892 (Box 271, Folder 21)
  - Photographs, 1892-1896 (Box 271, Folder 22)
  - Photographs, 1897-1900 (Box 271, Folder 23)
  - Photographs, 1901-1919 (Box 271, Folder 24)
  - Photographs, 1920- (Box 271, Folder 25)
  - Photographs-birthday party, 1956 (Box 271, Folder 26)
  - "The Reel", 1933-1935 (Box 272, Folder 1)
  - "The Reel", 1952-1953 (Box 272, Folder 2)
  - Resignation, 1936-1955 (Box 272, Folder 3)
  - 75th anniversary - correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 272, Folder 4)
  - Smith clubs: a suggestion from Ford, 1932 (Box 272, Folder 5)
  - Smith primer (facts about Smith College), 1946; undated (Box 272, Folder 6)
  - Snow, Florence H. - retirement skit, 1948 (Box 272, Folder 7)
  - Trustee appointment, 1931 (Box 272, Folder 8)
  - Trustees - criticism - Barnes, H.E., 1928-1934 (Box 272, Folder 9)
  - Trustees - criticism - Parshley, H., 1934 (Box 272, Folder 10)
  - Trustees - meetings, 1931 (Box 272, Folder 11)
  - Trustees - reports, undated (Box 272, Folder 12)
  - United Nations Weekend at Smith (correspondence, articles, and photographs), 1948-1949 (Box 272, Folder 13)
  - War bond campaign (clippings and propaganda), 1942-1945 (Box 272, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Ford, Harriet (Bliss) (1899), 1936; undated (Box 273, Folder 1)
  - Alumnae Association, 1936-1937; undated (Box 273, Folder 2)
  - Anderson, Dorothy May, 1936 (Box 273, Folder 3)
  - Baldwin, Ruth (Bowles) (1887), 1932 (Box 273, Folder 4)
  - Bacon, Josephine (Daskam) (1898), 1921 (Box 273, Folder 5)
  - Berliss, Ruth Ernestine (1932) (Box 273, Folder 6)
  - Bolster, Susanne (Ricker), 1934 (Box 273, Folder 7)
  - Chase, Mary Ellen, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 8)
  - Churchill, Ruth (Pierson) (1919), 1949-1950 (Box 273, Folder 9)
  - Comstock, Ada Louise (1897), 1931-1955 (Box 273, Folder 10)
  - Conkling, Grace (Hazard) (1899), 1924 (Box 273, Folder 11)
  - Cutter, Annie Spencer, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 12)
  - Davidson, Adaline (Allen) (1890), 1933 (Box 273, Folder 13)
  - Davis, Hallie Flanagan, 1952 (Box 273, Folder 14)
  - Development fund, 1962 (Box 273, Folder 15)
  - Eller, Alice (Seely) (1926), 1935 (Box 273, Folder 16)
  - Emerson, Kendall, 1932 (Box 273, Folder 17)
  - Evans, Bess Orr (ex-1933), 1935 (Box 273, Folder 18)
  - Finley, John Huston, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 19)
  - Gleason, Emily (Clapp) (1916), 1936 (Box 273, Folder 20)
  - Grierson, Margaret (Storrs) (1922), 1948-1956 (Box 273, Folder 21)
  - Hill, Edith Naomi (1903), undated (Box 273, Folder 22)
  - Hodgkinson, Laura (Cabot) (1922), 1952-1953 (Box 273, Folder 23)
  - Kimball, Charlotte (Smith) (1909), undated (Box 273, Folder 24)
  - League of Women Voters, 1932 (Box 273, Folder 25)
  - Martin, Caro (Taylor) (1891), 1931 (Box 273, Folder 26)
  - Morrow, Elizabeth (Cutter) (1896), 1930-1939 (Box 273, Folder 27)
  - Murphy, Mary Carolyn (1934) (Box 273, Folder 28)
  - Neilson, William Allan, 1929-1953 (Box 273, Folder 29)
  - Neilson, William Allan - faculty salaries, 1927-1928 (Box 273, Folder 30)
  - "New Creation" - correspondence regarding, 1930; undated (Box 273, Folder 31)
  - Norton, Katherine (Garrison) (1895), undated (Box 273, Folder 32)
  - Perkins, James H., 1932 (Box 273, Folder 33)
  - Prince, Winifred (Notman) (1911), 1925 (Box 273, Folder 34)
  - Rausch, Louise (Cornell) (1913), 1932 (Box 273, Folder 35)
  - Ripperger, Henrietta (Sperry) (1910), 1932 (Box 273, Folder 36)
  - Sabin, Florence Rena (1893), 1935 (Box 273, Folder 37)
  - Spahr, Jean (Fine) (1883), 1928 (Box 273, Folder 38)
  - Teagle, Alice (Wright) (1904), 1932-1935 (Box 273, Folder 39)
  - Wells, Marguerite Milton (1895), undated (Box 273, Folder 40)
  - Wright, Benjamin Fletcher, 1950-1956 (Box 273, Folder 41)
  - Zinsser, Dorothy (Douglas) (1913), 1935 (Box 273, Folder 42)
- SERIES III. SPEECHES
  - General, 1944-1953 (Box 273, Folder 43)
  - Anniversary, 1925 (Box 273, Folder 44)
  - Alumnae Association, 1926 (Box 273, Folder 45)
  - Alumnae Association, 1927 (Box 273, Folder 46)
  - Alumnae Association, 1928 (Box 273, Folder 47)
  - Alumnae Association, 1929 (Box 273, Folder 48)
  - Alumnae Association, 1932 (Box 273, Folder 49)
  - Alumnae Association, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 50)
  - Alumnae Association, 1936 (Box 273, Folder 51)
  - Alumnae Council, 1932 (Box 273, Folder 52)
  - Alumnae Council, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 53)
  - Alumnae Council, 1936 (Box 273, Folder 54)
  - Baldwin House round table, undated (Box 273, Folder 55)
  - Bennett School - Buffalo, NY, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 56)
  - Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 57)
  - Burnham School, 1950-1952 (Box 273, Folder 58)
  - Class of 1899, 1899-1909; undated (Box 273, Folder 59)
  - Class of 1924 (Box 273, Folder 60)
  - Class of 1927, 1947 (Box 273, Folder 61)
  - Growth in Opportunities for Women, undated (Box 273, Folder 62)
  - M.I.T. student visitors, undated (Box 273, Folder 63)
  - Press Board, 1933 (Box 273, Folder 64)
  - Smith clubs, 1933-1934; undated (Box 273, Folder 65)
  - Smith in Washington, 1934-1935 (Box 273, Folder 66)
  - Student assembly, 1932 (Box 273, Folder 67)
  - Student assembly, 1934 (Box 273, Folder 68)
  - Student assembly, 1935 (Box 273, Folder 69)
  - Student assembly, 1936 (Box 273, Folder 70)
  - Student assembly, 1946 (Box 273, Folder 71)
- SERIES IV: TOURS
  - Tour 1, 1933; undated (Box 274, Folder 1)
  - Tour 1 - Alumnae Association, 1933 (Box 274, Folder 2)
  - Tour 1 - Dallas, 1933-1934 (Box 274, Folder 3)
  - Tour 1 - Denver, 1933 (Box 274, Folder 4)
  - Tour 1 - Kansas City, 1933 (Box 274, Folder 5)
  - Tour 1 - Omaha, 1933 (Box 274, Folder 6)
  - Tour 1 - St. Louis, 1933; undated (Box 274, Folder 7)
  - Tour 1 - Tulsa, 1933-1934 (Box 274, Folder 8)
  - Tour 2, 1934 (Box 274, Folder 9)
  - Tour 2 - Atlanta, 1934 (Box 274, Folder 10)
  - Tour 2 - Augusta/Charlotte/Charleston/Richmond, 1934 (Box 274, Folder 11)
  - Tour 2 - Wilmington, 1935 (Box 274, Folder 12)
  - Tour 2 - Winston/Salem, 1932-1934 (Box 274, Folder 13)
  - Tour 3, 1934-1935 (Box 274, Folder 14)
  - Tour 3 - Duluth, 1934-1935 (Box 274, Folder 15)
  - Tour 3 - Milwaukee, 1934 (Box 274, Folder 16)
  - Tour 3 - Minneapolis/Oshkosh, 1934; undated (Box 274, Folder 17)
  - Tour 3 - St. Paul, undated (Box 274, Folder 18)
  - Tour 3 - South Bend, 1934; undated (Box 274, Folder 19)
  - Tour 4, 1936 (Box 274, Folder 20)
  - Tour 5, 1935-1936 (Box 274, Folder 21)
  - Tour 5 - Albuquerque, 1936 (Box 274, Folder 22)
  - Tour 5 - Alumnae Association, 1935-1936 (Box 274, Folder 23)
  - Tour 5 - California, 1936 (Box 274, Folder 24)
  - Tour 5 - Santa Fe, 1936 (Box 274, Folder 25)
  - Tour 5 - Washington, 1936 (Box 274, Folder 26)
- SERIES V: PUBLICATIONS
  - The Cricket, 1904 (Box 275, Folder 1)
  - A House for the Towne, 1952-1955 (Box 275, Folder 2)
  - In the Smith Tradition, 1945-1946 (Box 275, Folder 3)
  - League of Nations, 1925; undated (Box 275, Folder 4)
  - March-Time Duet, 1935 (Box 275, Folder 5)
  - The Minor Poet, undated (Box 275, Folder 6)
  - Poetry scrapbook, 1896-1928 (Box 275, Folder 7)
  - Return of a Native, undated (Box 275, Folder 8)
  - Smith College Weekly editorial, 1933 (Box 275, Folder 9)
  - Stephen Phillips, 1903 (Box 275, Folder 10)
  - The Tel Club, undated (Box 275, Folder 11)
  - The Trustees Look at the Future, 1932 (Box 275, Folder 12)